L. Eugene Thomas Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
L. Eugene Thomas Papers.
undated, 1979-1990.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Thomas, L. Eugene.
2.6 linear feet.
L. Eugene Thomas was a professor in the Department of Family Studies at the University of Connecticut for many years. Much of his research was focused on the psychology of personality, specifically as it applies to human aging.
MSS19980309
Biography
L. Eugene Thomas was born in Magnolia, Arkansas on 27 December 1932, and received his B.A. degree from Louisiana State University in 1955. He continued his education with a Masters in Divinity from Union Theological Seminary, a Masters in 1966 from the University of Chicago and two years later his doctorate, also from the University of Chicago.; L. Eugene Thomas was a professor in the Department of Family Studies at the University of Connecticut for many years having been appointed in 1968 and becoming a full professor in 1982. Thomas received numerous awards and fellowships including American Institute of Indian Studies, Senior Research Fellowship (India, 1983) and Senior Fulbright Research Fellowship (India, 1989-1990; Turkey, 1996-1997)
Much of his research was focused on the psychology of personality, specifically as it applies to human aging. Some of Prof. Thomas' later research focused more specifically on the relationship between psychological maturity and spiritual transcendence in subjects he described as 'spiritually advanced.' Prof. Thomas utilized research methods derived from qualitative rather than quantitative analysis. Thus, rather than performing statistical studies on large populations, Prof. Thomas performed close linguistic analysis of transcripts from carefully selected interview subjects.
Dr. Thomas died in 1998.
Scope and Content
Most of Dr. Thomas' research is concerned with the idea of “successful” aging. The interview transcripts included with this collection are part of an extended project involving the comparison of developmental maturity in elderly persons across differing cultural contexts. To quote from a letter that Dr. Thomas wrote in 1983, “I am interested in exploring why some people age gracefully, while others become fearful and bitter.” Dr. Thomas made at least two extended trips to India - one in 1983 and the other in 1989-90. During each of these two sabbaticals Dr. Thomas also made a stay in England on his return from India and collected additional interview samples there. Thus, chronologically, the segment of the collection titled “Indian Interviews I” comes just before “English Interviews I” though the two projects are conceptually inter-related. The first collection of Indian interviews focuses on elderly householders in Varanasi, India (near New Delhi). The subjects are mostly male, and all speak English. Most are somewhat affluent, but there is some diversity in professions and economic status. The first segment of English interviews is likewise focused on elderly men. Not all of these transcripts are complete - many folders only contain answers to certain key questions. Note that Dr. Thomas was able to contact several of the English subjects for follow-up interviews in 1990, though these later interviews are not otherwise related to the main series of 1990 interviews.
In 1989 Dr. Thomas undertook a new series of Indian interviews, this time focusing more specifically on religious “renouncers”, or individuals who had renounced their families in later years in order to prepare themselves for death. All of the interviews were conducted in or near a religious commune or ashram in Varanasi, India. Many of the subjects are swamis, specifically chosen as part of Dr. Thomas' efforts to study 'spiritually advanced practitioners.' These interviews are more open-ended than the earlier series, and some are quite extensive. The related series, identified as “English Interviews II” in this collection, dates from 1990 and concerns a closely knit group of elderly church-goers in Birmingham, England. One of the subjects is an Anglican bishop. As in all of these interviews, the scientific method involves a phenomenological approach analysis metaphor and thematic content in the interview transcripts. The psychological theories are derived in large part from the work of Erikson. The collection contains sporadic manuscript notes by Dr. Thomas illustrating his phenomenological method for selected subjects.
Arrangement
Collection consists of a single series, divided into four main groupings. “Indian Interviews I” and “English Interviews I” both date from 1983, though some of the related correspondence and several follow-up interviews fall outside this one year. The transcripts in “Indian Interviews II” were gathered in 1989-90, while the transcripts in “English Interviews II” were gathered in 1990.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal papers.; University of Connecticut--Dept. of Family Studies.
Subjects:
Psychology.; Older people--Psychology.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Print Materials.; Interview Transcripts.
Occupations:
Educators, American.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated to Archives & Special Collections by the widow of L. Eugene Thomas in 1998.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1979-1990
  - Indian Interviews I: Contact Letters, 1982-1988 (Box 1)
  - Indian Interviews I: 'Tales from the Vedas' article, 1979
  - Indian Interviews I: 'Health Locus of Control', undated
  - Indian Interviews I: Interview Question Lists, ca. 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: Factual Question Worksheets, subjects 2-51, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #1 - Abdul Bari (incomplete transcript), 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #2 - Shri Bal Kishan, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #3 - Bal Mokand Vig, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #4 - Shri B. C. Majumdar, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #5 - B. G. K. Rao, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #6 - Bhagmal Kwatra, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #7 - Dr. Bhagwan Datt, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #8 - RaiSaheb Devi Dayal Verma, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #9 - Dinanath Nijhawan, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #10 - Gopi Chand Gupta, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #11 - Sardar Gurbachan Singh, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #12 - Shri Guru Datt Thanda, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #13 - Hansraj Govan, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #14 - Harnam Dass, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #15 - Jagan Nath Paul, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #16 - J. D. Thukral, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #17 - Dr. Jeet Raj Sudan, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #18 - Kailash Chand, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #19 - K. G. Sahni, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #20 - Mrs. Kamala Behl, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #21 - Kartar Singh, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #22 - Madan Mohan Lal, 1983
    (#23 not present)
  - Indian Interviews I: #24 - Mujtafa Hussain Zaide, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #25 - N. C. Bhattacharyya, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #26 - Nahar Singh, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #27 - N. C. Sircar, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #28 - Shri Nihal Chand Gupta, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #29 - Prof. Parkash Lal Kocchar, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #30 - Major Partap Singh, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #31 - Mrs. Raj Kaushaliya Kapoor, 1983
    (second phase missing)
  - Indian Interviews I: #32 - R. K. Bhutani, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #33 - Dr. Ram Soop, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #34 - Dr. Roshan Lal Chibber, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #35 - R. R. Chapra, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #36 - Dr. Saifi Prem, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #37 - Dr. Salamatullah, 1983
    (#38 not present)
  - Indian Interviews I: #39 - Dr. Shivcharan Singh Datta, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #40 - Shiv Nath Wadhaven, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #41 - S. L. Puri, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #42 - S. L. Sahni, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #43 - S. L. Tuli, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #44 - S. S. Ramakrishnan, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #45 - Suchet Singh, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #46 - Syed Hussain, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #47 - T. A. Aiyar, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #48 - Shri T. C. Sanyal, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #49 - T. V. Ramamurthy, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #50 - Shri V. D. Sharma, 1983
  - Indian Interviews I: #51 - V. S. Dutta, 1983
  - English Interviews I: Interview Questions and Content Analysis, 1983-1988
  - English Interviews I: Contact Sheet and Spiritual Coding, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: Themes and Notes, ca. 1988
  - English Interviews I: #1 - Mathews, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #2 - L. Potiphar, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #3 - Noaker, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #4 - Einthorn, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #5 - Oulpe, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #6 - Mr. Bentley, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #7 - Mr. Coghill, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #8 - Mr. Wilson, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #9 - Mr. Bird, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #10 - Lindelauf, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #11 - Mr. Guppy, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #12 - Mr. Dunstan, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #13 - Mr. Pasco, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #14 - Mr. C. Gray, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #15 - Raymond Ford, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #16 - Mr. Cotton, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #17 - Mr. Cohen, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #18 - Mr. Rennie, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #19 - Mr. Kinsey, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #20 - Mr. Parker, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #21 - Mr. Nicholas, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #22 - Mr. Olsson (includes 'Meaning Units' and Theme Summary), ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #23 - Mr. Bowden, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #24 - Mr. Bishop, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #25 - Mr. Doran, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #26 - Mr. Symberlist, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #27 - Mr. Dyson, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #28 - Mr. Kane, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #29 - Mr. Brown, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #30 - Mr. Milledge, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #31 - Mr. Uhlman (includes themes and meaning units), ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #32 - A. J. Ryder, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #33 - Mr. Bloomfield, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #34 - Mr. Eburn, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #35 - Sheldrick, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #36 - Mr. Cole, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #37 - Mr. Metcalf, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #38 - Mr. Coghill (not same as #7), ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #39 - Mr. McDougal, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #40 - Roy Jarvis, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #41 - Mr. Gillespie, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #42 - Mr. Silk, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #43 - Mr. Kroker, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #44 - Mr. Swain, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #45 - Mr. Shepherd, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #46 - Mr. Stoate, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #47 - Mr. Smith, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #48 - Mr. Fairman, ca. 1983
  - English Interviews I: #49 - Norman Oliver, 1983, 1990
  - English Interviews I: #50 - George Jaegger, 1983, 1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Research Proposal Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Indian Interviews II: Notes and Preliminary Research Prospectus, ca. 1987
  - Indian Interviews II: Contact Notes and Correspondence, 1987-1989
  - Indian Interviews II: Research Notes and Support Articles, ca. 1983-1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Interview Question Sheets, ca. 1989
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Vedant Anandi, 1989
  - Indian Interviews II: Pundit Misra, 1989
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Muktananda, 1989
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Gangeshwarandand (w/ Sw. Tewari), 1989
  - Indian Interviews II: Bramacharya Ramshiva (includes related correspondence and copy of a Hindu prayer), 1989-1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Tewari, 1989-1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Shankashram, 1989-1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Tambe, Folder I, 1989-1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Tambe, Folder II, 1989-1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Tambe, Folder III, 1989-1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Family of Sw. Tambe, 1989
  - Indian Interviews II: Sw. Dhiranand, includes analysis, 1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Babaji, 1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Jayantilal Parekh, 1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Marguerite Smithwhite, 1990
  - Indian Interviews II: Tehmi, 1990
  - English Interviews II: Project Notes and Content Analysis, ca. 1990
  - English Interviews II: Project Notes and Contact Sheets, ca. 1990
  - English Interviews II: #101 - Mary Bangert (includes analysis), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #102 - Harry Bangert, 1990
  - English Interviews II: #103 - Irving Barnes (includes analysis), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #104 - Sylvia Barnes (includes analysis), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #105 - Dan Beeby (includes analysis), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #106 - Bill Burcham, 1990
    (#107 not present)
  - English Interviews II: #108 - Frieda Davey (includes analysis), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #109 - Jenny Gaman, 1990
  - English Interviews II: #110 - Ken Hooper, 1990
  - English Interviews II: #111 - Leslie Newbigin (includes analysis and two articles written by subject), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #112 - Edwin Norris, 1990
  - English Interviews II: #113 - Christine Stoddard (includes analysis and note written by subject), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #114 - Marjorie Sykes, 1990
  - English Interviews II: #115 - Janet Tompkinson, 1990
  - English Interviews II: #116 - Mary Worrall (includes analysis), 1990
  - English Interviews II: #117 - Stanley Worrall (includes analysis), 1990